Guide to the Holmes Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Holmes family papers
1823-1896
1856-1896
MS 1000
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The principal figure in these papers is Charles Edward Latimer Holmes, of Waterbury and Bridgeport, Connecticut, manufacturer of brass and silver, and the son of Israel Holmes. Included are correspondence, business papers, a diary, and family scrapbooks. Holmes' letters to his second wife, Annie E. Slade Holmes, and his daughter, Lydia Holmes Bliss, were chiefly written while he was traveling on business to France and England in 1879 and to England in 1883. His business papers consist of letter books (1881-1883) and correspondence and patents related to his inventions (1879-1883). Also in the papers is a diary kept by his first wife, Mary E. Steele Holmes, while they were living in Nebraska in 1856. Of the two scrapbooks, one contains letters from his uncle, Reuben Holmes, while the second was kept by a member of the Israel Holmes family and contains clippings, letterheads from the family businesses, programs, speeches, poems by C. E. L. Holmes, and other memorabilia.
Holmes family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Arthur B. Dayton, 1955.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Holmes Family Papers consist mainly of personal letters and business papers of C. E. L. Holmes (1832-1884) and scrapbooks documenting his literary career. The personal letters, 1864-1884, were addressed to his second wife, Annie E. (Slade) Holmes, and his daughter, Lydia (Holmes) Bliss, while he was doing business in New York and Connecticut and traveling to England (1879, 1883) and France (1879). The business papers are mainly letterbooks, 1881-1883, and correspondence and patents related to his inventions, 1879-1883. The scrapbooks contain clippings and a few manuscripts of his poems and prose plus several business cards from manufacturing enterprises with which he was associated.
There are also a few papers of other family members: a diary, "First Housekeeping," by his first wife, Mary (Steele) Holmes (d. 1862), kept while they were living in Nebraska in 1856; some printed and manuscript poems and prose by his father, Israel Holmes (1800-1874); and copies of several letters, 1823, written by his father's brother, Reuben Holmes (1798-1833), around the time he was graduated from West Point.
The Holmes Family Papers were given to Yale University Library by Mrs. Arthur B. Dayton in 1955.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Edward Latimer Holmes was born in Waterbury, Connecticut, on May 15, 1832. He had little education and entered the manufacturing business at seventeen. In 1857, he moved to Nebraska, but returned in 1860. During the Civil War, he helped to organize the 23rd regiment of Connecticut volunteers and, after being appointed colonel, was sent to fight in Louisiana. After the war, he returned to the manufacturing business. He was married twice and had a daughter by the second marriage. Holmes died on April 28, 1884.
Business; Families; Inventions; Literature -- History and criticism; Connecticut -- Industry; Europe -- Description and travel; Great Britain; Nebraska -- Social life and customs; West (U.S.); Diaries; Scrapbooks; Businessmen; Manufacturers; Holmes, Charles Edward Latimer, 1832-1884; Holmes, Israel, 1800-1874; Holmes, Mary E. Steele, d. 1862; Holmes, Reuben, 1798-1833; Holmes family
- Inventory
  - Charles E. L. Holmes
    - Correspondence, 1859-1884 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 8)
    - Letterbooks, 1881-1883 (Box 1, Folder 8A-8B)
    - Papers relating to patents for sewing machine improvements and other inventions, 1873-1882 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Business letters and papers, 1879-1883, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ms. speech and printed poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Printed passenger list from the steamship Baltic, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Printed copy of photograph, undated
  - Charles E. L. and Mary E. (Steade) Holmes: diary, "First Housekeeping", 1856 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Israel Holmes: printed address and poem, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Volume containing letters by Reuben Holmes, ms. poem by Israel Holmes, and clippings of poems and addresses, 1823, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Volume of printed writings, 1870, 1873, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Volume containing printed and ms. poems, clippings, programs, business cards, etc., many relating to Charles E. L. Holmes, 1870-1873, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters patent issued to John Ingraham, 1868 December 1 (Box 3)
  - Letters patent issued to Edwin Powley Alexander, 1880 March 15 (Box 3)
  - Autographs (Box 3)
  - Sarah Potter (1813-1900), 1896 February 3 (Box 3)
    - Elizabeth, queen consort of George VI, undated (Box 3)